<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The fifteen joys of marriage.]</title>
            <title>Quinze joyes de mariage. English</title>
            <author>La Sale, Antoine de, b. 1388?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1507</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15257.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125062</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898908</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898908</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150999</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150999)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1994:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The fifteen joys of marriage.]</title>
                  <title>Quinze joyes de mariage. English</title>
                  <author>La Sale, Antoine de, b. 1388?</author>
                  <author>Copland, Robert, fl. 1508-1547, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4+] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1507]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation in verse, possibly by Robert Copland, of: La Sale, Antoine de.  Quinze joyes de mariage--STC.</note>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="fragment_of_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:150999:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150999:1"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <div type="part">
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>She ſholde not goo / this make I goo auow</l>
               <l>Ha my good ſone ſhe ſayth by heuen kynge</l>
               <l>That made this worlde / and euery other thynge</l>
               <l>Ye may as ſurely and withouten drede</l>
               <l>Suffre her to go as for to ſaye your crede</l>
               <l>Thus they departe and on theyr waye be gone</l>
               <l>And as they goo / theſe wordes than ſayth one</l>
               <l>Vnto an other he hath ſome Ialouſye</l>
               <l>It ſemeth wele he dredeth Ieopardye</l>
               <l>Thus is he mocked by theſe womens arte</l>
               <l>For now come galauntes forth on euery parte</l>
               <l>Whiche at the feeſt afore by auenture</l>
               <l>This foreſayd werke haue made and put in vre</l>
               <l>And there awaytynge ben vpon theyr nede</l>
               <l>For to conclude and ſo forth to procede</l>
               <l>But how this wyfe now feſted is &amp; ſerued</l>
               <l>For loue of her good man all vndeſerued</l>
               <l>And god wote how ſhe doth her ſelfe applye</l>
               <l>To reuell dauncé / and for to ſynge on hye</l>
               <l>Alſo ſhe maketh good and mery chere</l>
               <l>But god wote how ſhe prayſeth her bedfere</l>
               <l>The huſbande lefte at home whyle ſhe is oute</l>
               <l>And ſeeth herſelfe ſo prayſed amonges the route</l>
               <l>Certes theſe galauntes than her do aduyſe</l>
               <l>And ſe ſhe is apparaylled in ſuche wyſe</l>
               <l>Perceyuynge well her chere and countenaunce</l>
               <l>Shortely to her eche one hym doth auaunce</l>
               <l>One profreth moche / an other offreth more</l>
               <l>Harde is to me the cauſe to tell wherfore</l>
               <l>The Ioly chere the praty trotte and pace</l>
               <l>With the demeanynge of a womans face</l>
               <l>Wyll gyue theſe louers cauſe &amp; hardyneſſe</l>
               <l>To ſewe for grace vnto theyr worthyneſſe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150999:2"/>
One to her wordes gracyous dooth ſaye</l>
               <l>An other cometh as nygh her as he may</l>
               <l>And ſetteth his fote a lofte on hers playne</l>
               <l>Eke by the honde quyckly he doth her ſtrayne</l>
               <l>Alſo an other his loke caſteth a ſyde</l>
               <l>Full pyteouſly and ſharpely for a tyde</l>
               <l>An other than vnto her dooth preſent</l>
               <l>A dyamonde ryght fayre and oryent</l>
               <l>Or elles a ryche rubye with a rynge</l>
               <l>Whiche ſhe receyueth with ſome other thynge</l>
               <l>By whiche thynges may ſhe well vnderſtande</l>
               <l>Of theyr entent / and fele it with her hande</l>
               <l>If ſhe haue ony reaſon brayne or wyt</l>
               <l>And other whyles by fortune happeth it</l>
               <l>That from her chayre alyght wyll ſhe adown</l>
               <l>To doo ſome werkes of deuocyon</l>
               <l>Or vnto Venus to doo ſacrefyſe</l>
               <l>But how can I not ſaye ne in what wyſe</l>
               <l>This ſely man at home in poore degree</l>
               <l>Is made and brought vnto neceſſytee</l>
               <l>For thylke eſtate that his wyfe doth pretende</l>
               <l>The mater thus hath dryuen to an ende</l>
               <l>And made her goo to gaderynges &amp; feeſtes</l>
               <l>Amonges a wycked company of geſtes</l>
               <l>For vnto her they yolden be in truſt</l>
               <l>To haue theyr pleaſures appetytes and luſt</l>
               <l>Vpon none other thynge do they aweyte</l>
               <l>But how they may doo this poore man deceyte</l>
               <l>The ſtroke wherof he hath without eſcape</l>
               <l>Whiche comynly is called but a Iape</l>
               <l>So he is cauſer of his propre ſhame</l>
               <l>None other wyght therof is for to blame</l>
               <l>And thus it happeth by contynuaunce</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150999:2"/>
That what by ſygnes ſpeche or countenaunce</l>
               <l>Trouth of the thynge wherof he was in doute</l>
               <l>All openly reported is aboute</l>
               <l>Wherby he falleth Ialouſe in a rage</l>
               <l>Out of the whiche there is no wyght ſo ſage</l>
               <l>That hym can moue / for who that feruently</l>
               <l>Of woman feieth the cruell malady</l>
               <l>There is noo medycyne that may hym cure</l>
               <l>The ſekeneſſe is ſo ſharpe without meſure</l>
               <l>Than wyll he bete her bytterly and curſe</l>
               <l>Wherby the werkes maketh he moche worſe</l>
               <l>For chaſtyce can he not by daye ne nyght</l>
               <l>His wyfe but by his betynge maketh lyght</l>
               <l>And hote the loue bytwene her &amp; her frende</l>
               <l>Thus dryueth he the mater to an ende</l>
               <l>And ſon he other whyles fortune may</l>
               <l>One of her lymmes breke or kytte away</l>
               <l>Wherby his caſtell or his pyle he loſeth</l>
               <l>Than as a maſed beeſt he hym dyſpoſeth</l>
               <l>Withouten care and all he ſetteth at nought</l>
               <l>Thus hath he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> payne whiche he hath ſought</l>
               <l>And neuer after wyll ſhe loue hym more</l>
               <l>Bycauſe that he hath beten her ſoo ſore</l>
               <l>But for to paſſe the tyme and make a ſhewe</l>
               <l>And of fayre wordes ſpeketh ſhe but fewe</l>
               <l>There this poore man in turment payne &amp; woo</l>
               <l>Lyueth and yet he thynketh not ſoo</l>
               <l>And all theſe ſorowes / he for Ioyes doth take</l>
               <l>Soo in the lepe he is I vndertake</l>
               <l>Encloſed depe / and yf he were withoute</l>
               <l>Yet ſhortely wolde he in withouten doute</l>
               <l>There vſeth he his lyfe in payne alwayes</l>
               <l>And wretchedly / thus endeth he his dayes</l>
               <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the ſeconde Ioye of maryage</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:150999:3"/>
               <head>¶ Here begynneth the thyrde Ioye of maryage.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>
                        <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <l>AN other Ioye whiche named is the thrydde</l>
               <l>Of maryage in no wyſe may be hydde</l>
               <l>The whiche I purpoſe ſhortely to declare</l>
               <l>Accordynge to myn auctour and not ſpare</l>
               <l>The whiche is whan a man in youth doth wedde</l>
               <l>A yonge mayde / and whan they bothe in bedde</l>
               <l>Haue had theyr pleaſures largely and deſyre</l>
               <l>And well aſwaged is the brennynge fyre</l>
               <l>The hoot herueſt is well ouerblowe</l>
               <l>As it with me and other is I trowe</l>
               <l>Soone after this her bely dooth aryſe</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:150999:3"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
